The last time I told you how to pass date to Git
Now let's see how to format date output
We'll use as a project the real repository
where Git is developed
we will format 'git log' date
because for the other commands
the process is the same
in ' --pretty' I will assign '%cd'
which means date of the commit in default format
then I will place commit header '%s'
to make the date shorter
let's configure it's format
'git log' command has for this purpose flag '--date'
other commands may have different approach to select the date format
which is followed by a format description
the default format is called pretty obvious
but there are some others formats.
For example 'rfc', 'iso'
and so on.
For practical use I draw them in a table.
Here we can notice that 'default' is almost alike with 'rfc'
the 'iso' date standard is shorter
But 'iso' has 2 variants. This is the usual one
and 'iso-strict' foremost used in programming
You can also set 'short' format - a date without time
'unix' timestamp
'raw' format - 'unix' timestamp with timezone
which is the internal format of the Git
and finally you can set 'relative' format
which is time offset for some time ago
For example, in our case
If we would set 'relative' format
you could find out that initially date is measured by days
then by weeks
after which by months and so on
this format is beautiful and short
and that its advantage. From the other side it is not always suitable in use
because it lacks accuracy
See, we have bunch of commits
But it is hard to distinguish which one was created 3 month ago
and which is 3 month and 4 weeks old.
Because each has same date -
approximately 3 months ago
If it fits your needs. It's fine. But if it's not
and you want a format other than those described
you can set your own format
you have to write 'format:'
and then percent designation for 'strftime'
it's known function for dates formatting
which Git is able to use
you can find function annotation separately in documentation
with detailed description
of the meaning of each percent designation and which date component it is related
The most used are '%H' - hours
small '%m' - number of month
capital '%M' - minutes, and so on.
Beside simple designations there are designation sets
For example, '%F' means Year-Month-Day, all at once
Same as if you would post those values through hyphens '%Y-%m-%d'
capital '%T' is full time format 24/24
Let's go back to our example, and set that the date
will be in format ':' and then
'%F' - Year-month-day.
'%T' - time
and the timezone
well
here it is
the format I created is identical to 'iso' integrated format
but we will try to improve it a little
First, notice that If you go further back through the history
the dates have different timezones
for current projects that's ordinary thing
because often developers are from different places of the world
and because Git stores date with the timezone
Actually, the dates are easy to understand and compare if they are in the same timezone
and preferably your current
Git for that purpose has suffix '-local'
it is added to any format, except 'raw' and 'unix'
and turns dates to local timezone
My actual timezone is +3. That's why
all dates are now formatted in timezone +3
Notice, when you are in predetermined timezone
there is no more need to output the timezone in date format
Unfortunately 'iso' is fixed format
so anytime timezone value is returned
but I will go back to format and add '-local'
'-local' means that the date should be reviewed and recounted
now I can exclude the timezone from there
Well. I got compact date in my timezone
Here I will end up with formats. As you may notice it has broad choose case
and flexibly to set up
As a conclusion, after my personal observations
i can affirm the most used formats are 'relative'
relative format
or the format in local timezone by the method i just showed.